<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods prerogative povver made known divers wayes in the Old and New Testament. Also the prerogative power of the Lord Christ. And what he will do in the dayes of his kingly office, in destroying his enemies, and exalting his saints. Very usefull for these times. / By him that loveth both truth and peace, Noah Banks.</title>
            <author>Banks, Noah.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E615_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865816</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865816</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78110)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E615[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods prerogative povver made known divers wayes in the Old and New Testament. Also the prerogative power of the Lord Christ. And what he will do in the dayes of his kingly office, in destroying his enemies, and exalting his saints. Very usefull for these times. / By him that loveth both truth and peace, Noah Banks.</title>
                  <author>Banks, Noah.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 13 (i.e. 21), [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.B. and are to be sold at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 21 is misnumbered 13.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS Prerogative Power Made known divers wayes in the Old and New Teſtament. ALSO The Prerogative Power of the <hi>Lord Chriſt.</hi> And what he will do in the dayes of his <hi>Kingly Office,</hi> In Deſtroying his Enemies, And Exalting his Saints. <hi>Very uſefull for theſe Times.</hi> By him that loveth both Truth and Peace, NOAH BANKS.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> R. B. <hi>and are to be ſold at the Weſt end of</hi> Pauls, 1650.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118067:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118067:2"/>
            <head>To the truely Honorable in Chriſt, Major General HARRISON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honored Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing that you are one that wait for the appearing of the Lord Chriſt in his Kingly glory, and are willing to hear news of the good Land, though it be by a weak &amp; poor inſtrument; for <hi>out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings, God will declare his praiſe.</hi> I have made bold to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat a few lines to your godly and grave conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, what I do believe God is doing in this laſt Age of the World; Surely, God is anſwering all the prayers, that have been powred out by the Saints at the Throne of Grace againſt Antichriſt, for this many hundred years; and he is now going in an eminent manner, to require the bloud of the Saints that hath been ſpilt by that man of ſin, and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; now the Lord is revenging the bloud of the Saints that cry under the Altar, now thoſe that have made war with the Lamb, the Lamb ſhall overcome them: for he, and he onely is Lord of Lords and King of Kings; and they that are with him are called <hi>choſen</hi> &amp; <hi>faithful.</hi> Antichriſt hath bin drunken with the bloud of the Saints, now he muſt have bloud to drink, for he is worthy; now have we great cauſe to bleſs God, who hath taken to himſelf great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and doth reign, and hath deſtroyed them that hath
<pb facs="tcp:118067:3"/> deſtroyed the earth; now is the Lord humbling great men, <hi>the loftineſs of man ſhall be bowed down and the haughtineſs of man shall be made low, and the Lord alone exalted in that day;</hi> now hath the Lord Chriſt appeared in the Majeſty of his ſtrength; in his Armies <hi>he hath ſcattered the proud in the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of their hearts, he hath pulled down the mighty from their ſeats, and exalted them of low degree; For behold, the day cometh that shall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea all that do wickedly shall be as ſtubble, and the day cometh that shall burn them up ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and it shall leave neither root nor branch; and he shall tread them down, and they shall be as aſhes under the ſoles of your feet; Now many Nations are gathered againſt thee, that ſay, let her be defiled, and let our eyes look upon</hi> Sion; <hi>but they know not the thoughts of the Lord, neither underſtand they his Counſel; he shall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them as Sheaves into the floores; Ariſe and thraſh O daughter of Sion for I will make thy horn iron, and thy hoofs braſs, and thou shalt beat in pieces many people;</hi> God doth and will do great things by weak inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thy feet ſhall tread them down, <hi>even the feet of the poor and the ſteps of the needy, Zech.</hi> 12. 8. and God hath made good his word of late, <hi>in that day shall the Lord defend the Inhabitants of</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>he that is fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amongſt them, shall be as</hi> David <hi>and the houſe of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>shall be as God, as the Angel of the Lord before them;</hi> God is now ſtayning the glory of all fleſh, now is the little Stone that was cut out of the Mountain without hands ſmiting the Image on the feet, that was of iron and clay and breaks them in pieces; then was the iron, and the clay and the braſs, and the ſilver, and the gold, and all the Empires of the earth broken in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:118067:3"/> together, and became like the chaff of the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer flower, and the wind carried them away, and the place was no more found: And the Stone that ſmot the Image became a great Mountain, and filled the whole earth; the Lord Chriſt will break them with a Rod of Iron, and daſh them in pieces like Potters veſſels; yea, the Kings of the earth that will not ſubmit to him, He will ſtrike through Kings in the day of his wrath, he will ſhake all Nations: yea, not only earth, but alſo Heaven; and theſe promiſes &amp; Prophecies &amp; many more, is the Lord Chriſt now making good by his <hi>Prerogative Power;</hi> and hath not God begun this work in this <hi>Common-wealth?</hi> hath not God delivered us out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by a mighty hand? and God hath broken the rod of oppreſſors, as in the day of <hi>Midean;</hi> and I do beleeve, the work that <hi>God</hi> hath begun in <hi>England</hi> ſhall go on till he hath made all his enemies his footſtool: and that great block that lyeth in the way, and hinders the peace of many good men, <hi>that the Witneſses are not ſlain:</hi> I do believe for my part, that the Witneſſes are ſlain in this Iland. I take the Witneſſes to be thoſe that have ſuffered under Antichriſt for fourty and two months, <hi>Rev</hi> 11. 2. as Antichriſt came in gradually, ſo ſhall his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical power be taken away gradually.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe when Chriſt begins he will make an end, <hi>Babylons</hi> ruine is like a mighty milſtone thrown in the Sea, it ſhall never be found again, he will goe <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 21.</note> on till <hi>Rome</hi> bee deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe in the time of Antichriſts reign the Witneſſes muſt be clothed in ſackcloth, but now <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 3.</note> God hath taken a way the ſackcloth, and many of the Saints doe ſee cauſe to put on the garment of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,
<pb facs="tcp:118067:4"/> and are wayting for the Bridegrooms coming.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Witneſſes having lain three dayes and a halfe dead, which is in conformity to Chriſts death, they muſt ſtand on their feet againe; as bleſſed bee God they now do in this Iland.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when the Witneſſes ſtand on their feet great feare ſhall fall on them that ſee them; and are not the enemies of Chriſt and his people in great feare in theſe daies who can but ſee it?</p>
            <p>Fiftly, and are not many of the Saints of Chriſt rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up by the Spirit of God into a glorious admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, and into a ſafe condition out of the reach of the malice and power of their enemies, and their enemies be hold them, but they cannot hurt <note place="margin">Rev. 13 6. Chap 12. 19.</note> them; Gods raiſing up his people is called heaven.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the great Earthquake God hath made of late both in <hi>England Ireland,</hi> and now of late in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which I doe beleeve hath made the territories of <hi>Babylon</hi> to ſhake, this is called a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake. <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, I do beleeve this Commonwealth was the tenth part of myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> which now is falen and the powers both in Church and Commonwelth that did oppreſs the ſaints is taking away bleſſed be the Lord; and is not the ſeventh Angel now going to ſound? and are there not great voices in heaven, in the Churches of Chriſt which is called heaven, ſaying the Kingdomes of the world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Lord and his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever, therefore let us <hi>fall down on our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> ſaying, <hi>we give thee thanks O Lord God almighty</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 11. 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great power and haſt reigned.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118067:4"/>
            <p>But now give me leave to give you a few Reaſons to ſhew you why I doe beleeve God is about ſuch a glorious work in this Iland.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe I do not know nor have read of any Iland in the Chriſtian world, that hath oppoſed the Lord Chriſt, but this, that hath a people that the Lord will ſave, at this time that the Lord is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Antichriſt, you may ſee in that forenamed <note place="margin">Iſa. 12. 14.</note> place.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in this Iland there hath bin many famous Martyrs that have ſuffered for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>God</hi> hath had as many <hi>Iacobs</hi> that have wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with <hi>God</hi> by prayer againſt Antichriſt as any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world ever had; and I can ſpeak it for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove this twenty years they have ſowen in tears, and were like unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> groning under our burdens and bondage, therefore I doe beleeve he is now bringing us out of bondage.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I doe beleeve God is going on with this his glorious work here in this Iland, becauſe <hi>God</hi> hath rayſed up choice Inſtruments in pulling down Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt powers that have oppoſed Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, God hath given many of his choice ſervants a great meaſure of faith, to beleeve that the work is begun in this Iland, and that it ſhall not end till An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, I am ſure of it God hath as many pretious and choyce ſervants, ſuch as doe love the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in ſincerity after the inward man, as any Nation in the world.</p>
            <p>Seventhly and laſtly, becauſe I doe find by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Chriſt, that his work in deſtroying Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall begin in the Ilands, as the Scripture ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:118067:5"/> 
               <hi>The Iles ſhall wayt for his Glory:</hi> So if you read the 97. Pſalm, the whol Pſalm is a glorious Prophecy of theſe Times: it begins, <hi>The Lord reigneth, let the Earth rejoyce, let the multitude of the Iles bee glad thereof.</hi> I do beleeve God has made good this whol Prophecy by his acts of Providence in this Iland, &amp; alſo that glorious prophecy in the 42 of Iſa. from <hi>verſe</hi> 12. to the 21. which I do believe is now fulfiling in theſe Ilands, and therefore we have no reaſon to murmur againſt the Inſtruments of our good, nor to complain, but to ſay with the Prophet in the 12. ver. <hi>let them give glory to the Lord and declare his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the Ilands:</hi> hath not the Lord Chriſt gone out like a mighty man? hath not hee cryed and roared againſt his enemies? hath not he made waſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and hills? hath not he brought the blind by away that they knew not, and led them in paths that they have not known? and made dark things light before them, and crooked things ſtraight: theſe things hath he done unto them, and not forſaken them; and may it not be ſaid at ſuch a time as this, who is blind but my ſervant? or deafe but my meſſinger as I have ſent, who is blind as he that is perfect &amp; blind as the Lords ſervant? ſeeing many things but obſerving it not: this prophecy I beleeve is fulfilled in our days.</p>
            <p>Sir this little Treatiſe was written ſome two years ſince, then being dark times, and therefore what you find of weakneſſe in it, let it be attributed to the author, but what you find to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mind of God, let him only have the glory: this Treatiſe was put forth by the deſire of many godly frinds, and beleeving you are one that is precious in the ſight of the Lord, therefore you will have a favorable conſtruction of what is written, I leave you in the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Lord Chriſt, <hi>NOAH BANKS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118067:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe laſt Ages of the world, there hath been much ado about the <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> of Kings, and great men in all Nations: ſo of late years more then formerly in this Iſland, as may appear by all thoſe wayes that great men took in oppreſsing the poor, in impoſing taxes on almoſt all wares, and in coat and conduct money, and Ship-money; which made the poor people to groan under their burthens, and to cry unto the Lord for vengeance againſt the oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>So alſo our Biſhops they lorded it over mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in bringing in Superſtitions and Idolatry, and ſeting up their <hi>Prerogative Power,</hi> that godly men muſt doe what their Wils will have, inſtead of Gods Word; ſo racking the conſciences of godly men till many times they crackt again, making ſome fly to <hi>New-England,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were impriſoned, branding ſome, and cuting off their ears; Oh how ſad was our condition then! ſome would by their <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> rule over the Eſtates of men, and others over the conſciences, it was worſe then <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> bondage; for they onely oppreſt the bodies, but theſe did ſeek to deſtroy both ſouls and bodies of men; and no viſible help could be found, becauſe they that had the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118067:6"/> 
               <hi>Power,</hi> called Parliaments, and broke them up again when they would not ſerve their wills: alſo over ruling Iuſtices and Iudges, they muſt bow the ſtrait Lawes, to ſerve their corrupt luſts, and like <hi>Iſſacar,</hi> we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſtoop under the burthen; but when men will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe their power, God will make them know, that he hath a power over them be they never ſo great; the want of the knowledge of that Almighty power that there is in God, and how he hath made known his <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> in all ages, is the cauſe men are ſo troubled in theſe times; but if men would ſearch the word of God, they would ſee how Gods wayes are in the deeps, and his footſteps are in the mighty waters. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 16. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Almighty, we cannot finde him out, he is excellent in power, he can throw down the walls of <hi>Iericho</hi> by the blowing of Rams horns, and open the eyes of one born blind with clay and ſpettle; he can make little <hi>David</hi> ſtrong enough to cut off the head of <hi>Goliah;</hi> and the Lord Chriſt choſe out poor Fiſhermen to be his Diſciples, and left the learned Scribes and Phariſees.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118067:6"/>
            <head>Gods <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> made known divers wayes in the Old Teſtament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe knowing times moſt men will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that all <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> is in God; but when God is making known his Power in ſome great acts of Providence in the world; oh how are moſt men offended at it, and will not beleeve farther then they can ſee by their dark light of naturall Reaſon: thus we read that good men failed much, as <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Job,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> till they went and ſearched into the word of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it will bee our wiſdomes in theſe troubleſom times &amp; dark &amp; various acts of Providence to ſearch the Scriptures how God hath formerly made known his Prerogative Power by moſt unlikely wayes and Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>Firſt when God brought the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> he commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to goe to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and tell him that the God of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> hath ſent to him to let his people go, but his anſwer was, I know not the Lord, neither will I let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go.</p>
            <p>Oh how unlikly a perſon was <hi>Moſes!</hi> a ſhepherd to go to ſo great a King in ſo ſtrange a buiſneſs, how hardly would <hi>Moſes</hi> be perſwaded, but when God ſaid he would make his Power known by plagueing <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Egyptians, and God ſaid he would goe with him; if God will goe with any Inſtruments they ſhall doe the work.</p>
            <p>God was not tied to raiſe a great Army, no he can make uſe of a Shepherd to doe the work, and he can arme Lice and Flies and Frogs to pull down the pride of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> But oh how hard a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was it for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to beleeve, becauſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did lay heavier
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118067:7"/> burdens on them then before; but after God had brought them out by a mighty hand, oh what an untroden path did God lead them in! they muſt goe thorow the Red Sea, or elſe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> would make them bond ſlaves or deſtroy them, now doth God make his <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> appeare above what <hi>Iſrael</hi> could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve by making a way for his people to goe thorow the Red Sea, when the Egyptians following them were all drowned; ſo all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long throw the wilderneſſe forty years did God preſerve them, in a miraculous way they had bread and meat from Heaven, and water out of a Rock, and yet for all this how few of them did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that God would bring them into <hi>Canaan</hi> and give them the Land of promiſe, none but <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb;</hi> one great reaſon was becauſe the walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> were ſo great and ſo high, but you may ſee how God did blow them downe with Rams hornes: How did <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the firſt hearing of their deliverance Reioyce and bow down their heads, and worſhip <hi>God,</hi> but after <hi>God</hi> had <note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.</note> made his Power known and brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> oh how did they murmur againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſaid <hi>they two took too much upon them;</hi> but did not <hi>God</hi> deſtroy them, and their carkaſſes fell in the Wilderneſſe for murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> So at the beginning of our Troubles, oh how did our Miniſters and People rejoyce and bleſſe <hi>God</hi> for rayſing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments to bring them out of Bondage; but now <hi>God</hi> having made his Power known by doing Wonders for us by them, oh how doe now the ſame men murmur againſt the ſame Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſay they take too much upon them, and fain would wee goe back again into <hi>Egypt</hi> but let theſe men take heed leſt <hi>God</hi> ſware in his wrath they ſhall never ſee the new <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> but their children ſhall ſee the good Land which many godly men now ſee a far off.</p>
            <p>Secondly how dark a way was that when Chriſt came at the firſt a Virgin ſhould conceive a ſonne! oh the mighty power of God, and love of this Lord and King of Heaven and Earth! He muſt come in the form of a Carpenters ſonne, none would own him but poore Shepherds, and Heathens; and afterwards he took poore Fiſhermen to be his Diſciples; and a few woemen admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to him! how did this blind the great Learned men of the Iewes! but here you ſee how God delights to make his <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118067:7"/> 
               <hi>Power</hi> known, when he will doe his greateſt works by the moſt unlikely Inſtruments: but oh how ſad a thing was it for them not to know in that their day the things that concerned their peace, and not to have rejected their Saviour: Oh let it not be ſayd of <hi>England</hi> nor <hi>London,</hi> that they doe ſlight or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the great Salvation that God hath done for us, becauſe the Inſtruments are not ſo great or ſo learned, leſt we <hi>be found fighters againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing God hath made his <hi>Prerogative</hi> formerly known by doing his greateſt works by the leaſt and unlikelieſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that all the glory may be given to him.</p>
            <p>So alſo doth the word of God declare his <hi>Prerogative Power;</hi> if you read the 32 of Deuteronomy from the 39 verſe to the 44 there God ſaith, <hi>I kill, I make alive, I wound, and I heale, and none can deliver out of my hands.</hi> So in the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> the ſecond chap: in the 7 and 8 verſes, <hi>the Lord maketh poore, and maketh rich, he bringeth low, and lifteth up; he rayſeth the poore out of the dunghill, to ſet them among Princes, and maketh them to inherit the Thrones of Glory: for the pillars of the Earth are the Lords, and he hath ſet the world on them.</hi> And in the 40 of <hi>Iob</hi> the 12 and 13 verſes. <hi>He looketh on every one that is proud, and bringeth him low; and treadeth down the wicked in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hideth them in the duſt together, and bindeth their faces in ſecret.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>Divers wayes did God make his</hi> Prerogatvie Power <hi>appeare in the Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt over Angels and Men, in pulling down their pride: The great Deſign God had in creating all things, was his own Glory, and amongſt all his creatures he made Angels and Men to be the moſt glorious; and endued them with many priviledges above all other creatures: but ſtill he reſerved the <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> to himſelfe. If the Angels (whom God had placed in an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent condition, who had Heaven for their habitation, ſtanding in the preſence of God beholding his glory) if they will not keep their firſt eſtate, but will lift up themſelves, God will then make known his Power in deſtroying them and all their glory, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118067:8"/> throwing them down out of heaven into hell, <hi>reſerving them in everlaſting chaines in utter darkneſſe unto the judgment of the great Day.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iud. ver. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And alſo <hi>Adam</hi> whom God created after his own image, and placed him in Paradiſe, and made him Lord over all his creatures here below, when hee would exalt himſelfe, how ſoon did God deſtroy him and all his glory, and his poſterity, and drove him out of Paradiſe; and hee and all creatures became accurſed: if <hi>Cain</hi> will lord it over his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſhed his brothers blood, God will make his Power known, he ſhall bee accurſed, and a vagabond on the earth. <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So if <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will deal proudly and ſay, <hi>who is the Lord?</hi> and by his power oppreſs Gods people with cruell bondage, and will <note place="margin">Exod. 5. 10.</note> not let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go at Gods command, God will make his Power appear in rayſing an Army of Lice, and Flies, and Frogs, to plague <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> and if this will not humble him, he hath a Red Sea wherein to drown him and all the malignant Egyptians that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after Gods people. <note place="margin">Exod, 14. 24.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> that proud King if hee lift up himſelfe, and ſay in the pride of his heart, <hi>Is not this great Babylon that I have built by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty?</hi> Here you ſee the pride of this vain man; but while the words were in the Kings mouth, God told him that the Kingdom was departed from him, and he was driven out from men; &amp; he did eat graſſe with the oxen; Oh let all proud Kings know <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 30. 31.</note> that the great God hath a <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> over them, he ruleth in the Kingdoms of men; he giveth them to whom ſo ever he will. <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So if <hi>Herod</hi> to whom <hi>God</hi> had given wiſdome, will harken to the applauſe of men, <hi>God</hi> will ſuddenly abaſe him, for the Text ſaith an Angell of God ſmot him, becauſe hee did not give the glory to <hi>God;</hi> hee was eaten up with Wormes and hee died. <note place="margin">Acts 12. 23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Examples and many more wee may ſee the great <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and how fearfull a thing it is to goe about to rob <hi>God</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative Power;</hi> this ſin hath always ſome Iudgment ſuddenly at the heeles of it, God doth many times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe ſuch proud men in this life, for pride goeth before deſtruction, <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 18.</note> and a high mind before the fall.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118067:8"/>
               <p>Secondly, Then <hi>God</hi> maketh his <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> appear, when <hi>God</hi> ſtops the natural courſe of his creatures, as when <hi>God</hi> at the prayer of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> made the Sun &amp; the Moon to ſtand <note place="margin">Ioſhua 10. 13.</note> ſtill, and the Sun to go back ten Degrees, and the fiery Oven not to burne the three Children, and the Lyons not to deſtroy <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 27. Exod. 14. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Red-Sea to ſtand like walls on both ſides, till <hi>Iſrael</hi> paſt over; <hi>God</hi> hath the <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> over all his creatures, if the Lord Chriſt command the Winds and the Seas they muſt obey him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>God</hi> maketh his <hi>Power</hi> known, when he maketh uſe of the weakeſt and baſeſt of his creatures, for to pull down the pride of man: as he did to proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he did ſend Frogs, Caterpillars, and Lice, and Flies, to plague <hi>Pharaoh</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 9.</note> and all <hi>Egypt;</hi> and alſo if proud <hi>Herod</hi> will take the glory to himſelf, which was due to <hi>God, God</hi> will ſend his Angel to ſmite him, and he ſhall be eaten up with Wormes.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Then <hi>God</hi> maketh his <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, when <hi>God</hi> makes uſe of the moſt unlikely inſtruments, to do the greateſt and moſt miraculous workes by: as when <hi>God</hi> threw down the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> with the blowing of Rams horns, and the Lord Chriſt opened the eyes of one that was born blind with clay and ſpettle, and <hi>Jonah</hi> muſt be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by being ſwallowed up of a great fiſh, which was a very unlikely way; but there is nothing too hard for <hi>God</hi> to do, he hath a <hi>Prerogative Power</hi> to do what he will, and by what means he will. See the 6.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>God</hi> maketh his mighty Power known, when he leadeth people in untrodden paths: as he did the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they muſt go through the Red Sea, and fourty years in the Wilderneſſe, and through the waters of <hi>Jordane;</hi> in all theſe wayes did <hi>God</hi> make his great Power appear ſo much the more: ſo alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the people of <hi>God</hi> in caſes of neceſſities, have gone in wayes that hath been contrary to the rule and revealed word; as <hi>David</hi> did when he did eat the Shew bread, which was lawfull for none but the Prieſt; yet Chriſt ſaid he was blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: ſo <hi>Phineas</hi> ſlew <hi>Zimry</hi> and <hi>Coſby,</hi> he being the high Prieſt it was not his place to execute juſtice; yet this act of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118067:9"/> was well pleaſing to <hi>God,</hi> and turned away the wrath of <hi>God</hi> from the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and how did God reward him and all the reſt that came after him. <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. 12.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The power of God appears, when God doth many times his greateſt workes by a few, and they the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible inſtruments. <hi>Gideons</hi> Army was too many. God would mould them, till they came but to three hundred, to overthrow the Hoaſt of the <hi>Midianites;</hi> which were as Graſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, <note place="margin">Iudges 7. 12.</note> and as the ſand of the Sea for number: So God thoſe out <hi>David</hi> to be King, the moſt unlikely of all the ſons of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> and he muſt fight with great <hi>Goliah,</hi> that made all the Army of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to tremble, whoſe ſpear was like a Weavers beam; yet this <hi>David</hi> whom his brethren diſpiſed he going in the name of the Lord killeth <hi>Goliah;</hi> here was the power of God the more ſeen! as when <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his Armor-bearer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforted the whole Hoaſt of the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> ſo the Lord Chriſt choſe poore Fiſher-men to be his Diſciples, and leaving the learned Scribes and Phariſees; thus God makes his power the more appear, when he does do great workes by weak in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; and hath not God done wonderfull things of late by a poore ſmall contemptible new-moddelled Army! how hath God by them routed great Armies, taken many ſtrong Garriſons! &amp; theſe laſt years it may be ſaid, what hath the Lord done by theſe deſpiſed inſtruments! oh what a black cloud was riſen in this poore land, in <hi>Wales,</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> and that great Army of the <hi>Scots</hi> never to be forgotten! and how did God by his poore inſtruments making them valiant, bring down the pride and power of theſe bloudy men! and ſurely if men were not blind, they would ſee how God doth own this Army! and if God own them, let men take heed how they ſpeak or act againſt them, leſt they be found fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; and God hath made his <hi>Prerogative power</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by this Army, that I am perſwaded that many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to come ſhall have cauſe to bleſſe God for them; and they having begun to throw down in this land the out-workes of <hi>Rome,</hi> who knoweth if God will not ſo highly honour ſome of them, that they may ſet up their Trophies on the walls of <hi>Rome!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118067:9"/>
               <p>Seventhly, God hath made his <hi>Prerogative power</hi> appear, in altering of the government of his Church five times already. Firſt, God let down a Government to <hi>Adam: Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> offered Sacrifice. Secondly, God let down a Patterne of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as you may reade in <hi>Leviticus.</hi> Thirdly, God did let down a farther way to <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> when the Temple was to be built. Fourthly, God let down to <hi>Ezra</hi> the ſecond Temple, the manner how it ſhould be built, and all things therein. Fifthly, The Lord Chriſt he comes and ſets up the Goſpel Government, which hath continued this ſixteen hundred years. Now there is one more Government ſpoken of in the 21. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. that is, the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> that muſt come down from Heaven, which will be a glorious time; this we waite for, which I beleeve will be the laſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on earth.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, So alſo the Lord hath made his <hi>Power</hi> appeare, by changing the Government in the Common-wealth: as firſt the Government was by <hi>Abraham</hi> the head of the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, ſecondly <hi>Moſes</hi> a Prophet, next <hi>Joſhua</hi> who was a Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo Judges continued, ſometimes they were men, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they were women, and thus it continued till <hi>Samuel's</hi> time: and this was the moſt immediate Government of God. But when <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have a King. God told them they had not onely rejected <hi>Samuel,</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> that he ſhould not rule over them; but then <hi>God</hi> changed the Government upon the requeſt of the people, and <hi>God</hi> bid <hi>Samuel</hi> go and anoint them a King; but <hi>God</hi> bid <hi>Samuel</hi> tell them the manner of the Kings that ſhould Reigne over them: how they would make ſlaves of them, and take away their eſtates from them; and hath not many Kings done ſo: did not <hi>Ahab</hi> take <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, and much of this hath been done in our dayes; then <hi>God</hi> gave them a King which was <hi>Saul,</hi> but did <hi>Saul</hi> and his <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 14, 15, 23.</note> ſons governe <hi>Iſrael</hi> long? No, <hi>God</hi> ſhewed his <hi>Prerogative</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> would not obey the command of <hi>God,</hi> but would fulfill his own will, <hi>God</hi> rejected him and his poſterity for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King, and ſet up <hi>David</hi> his ſervant in his place; and many times did <hi>God</hi> throw down Kings, as he did <hi>Ahab,</hi> and ſet up others in their ſtead; but when <hi>Iſrael</hi> and their Kings begun
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118067:10"/> to ſin with a high hand againſt <hi>God,</hi> and would not repent, then <hi>God</hi> gave them and their King into the hand of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, whom they would be like in having a King, as you may read, <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5. then was <hi>Iſrael</hi> brought under the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Monarchy: Four Monarchies have been already, firſt the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh</hi> Monarchy ſecondly the <hi>Perſian,</hi> thirdly the <hi>Grecian,</hi> fourthly the <hi>Roman;</hi> all which Monarchies were ſhown to <hi>Daniel</hi> in the dream. Now the laſt which is the fifth, which is ſaid to be a Little ſtone cut out of the Mountaine without hands, as you may read, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 34, 36. Now begun the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Power</hi> of the Lord Chriſt; for it is ſaid, <hi>He ſmote the Image on the feet, that were made of Iron and Clay,</hi> and brought to nothing all the other Monarchies, as you may read, <hi>ver.</hi> 35. <hi>and it became a great mountaine, and filled the whole earth;</hi> this is a ſtone cut out without hands, a Kingdom ſet up by the <hi>God</hi> of Heaven, ſome divine work: and all the Kingdoms and States that were firſt and laſt, ſhall be ſwallowed up under this Kingdom of Chriſt, as appears, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>There was given to him Dominion and Glory, and a Kingdom, that all Nations and Languages ſhall ſerve him: his Dominion is an everlaſting Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, that ſhall not paſſe away; and his Kingdom ſhall not be deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118067:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Gods</hi> Prerogative Power <hi>made known in the New Teſtament, and in theſe laſt ages of the World.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THus having ſpoken ſomething of the <hi>Prerogative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of God in the former ages, now much might be ſaid of the Power of the Lord Chriſt in theſe laſt ages of the world.</p>
            <p>In the firſt ages, Chriſt did wonderfully and gloriouſly make known his Prophetical Office, viſibly and externally in the world by all the Prophets, as <hi>Iſaiah, David, Daniel,</hi> and all the reſt of the Prophets: ſo alſo he was held forth typically in the Cloud, in the Pillar of fire in the Rock, in the brazen Serpent, in the Arke and Tabernacle, and in the Temple, and all the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, and the High Prieſts, the Scape Goate; all theſe did hold forth the Prophetical Office of Chriſt, in thoſe dayes of his Prophecy very gloriouſly, to all thoſe that underſtood the Prophecies. <hi>Abraham</hi> rejoyced to ſee the dayes of Chriſt, and <hi>Daniel</hi> longed to underſtand the viſion: and oh that men would more ſtudy to underſtand the Old Teſtament; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might ſee what God would do in all ages.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond age of the world was the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt made known viſibly, externally, and gloriouſly in the world, to the amazement both of men and Angels and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils; God teſtifies of him, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. 17. this is my beloved ſon whom I promiſed ſhould come in the fulneſs of time to brake the Serpents head: alſo the Angels ſpake glorious things of a Saviour that was born, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 10. ſo the wiſe men they,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118067:11"/> came from far to ſee this great High Prieſt; and the Apoſtles were witneſſes of all Chriſt did in the adminiſtration of his Prieſtly Office, the Devils confeſt him, and Soldiers, and Chriſt himſelf was crucified openly on the Croſſe; all theſe do declare, that in the ſecond age of the world, the Lord Chriſt did openly in the ſight of men and Devils, fullfil all Promiſes concerning his Prieſtly Office; and all the Saints muſt ever ſince fill up the meaſure of the ſufferings of Chriſt openly, for conformity to Chriſt this ſixteen hundred years.</p>
            <p>The Lord Chriſt having finiſhed his two Offices, a Prophet and a Prieſt; now he ſhall come as King, and we have great ground to believe it, as you may read hereafter, that the Lord Chriſt is coming to ſet up his <hi>Prerogative power;</hi> for now God the Father hath given to his Son all power both in Heaven and earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 18. now of his enemies that would not have him rule over them, he ſaith, <hi>bring them and ſlay them before me;</hi> now God will give his Son <hi>the Heathen for his inheritance, and the utmoſt part of the earth for his poſſeſſion, Pſa.</hi> 2. 8. the Lord Chriſt hath hitherto been but a ſuffering and a perſecuted King, a ſcoft and a deſpiſed King by the Kings of the world; but now he will be Lord and King of the whole earth. <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. 9.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord Chriſt a ſumes to himſelf a new form, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the form of a ſervant; he is now coming to ſet up his <hi>Prerogative Kingly power,</hi> to ſhew to his Saints and to his enemies, the great deſign he is doing in the world; this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt will be very ſweet and comfortable to his Saints, but terrible to his enemies, with an iron rod in his hand, and he ſhall daſh them in pieces like Pottets veſſels, and he ſhall have his Garments dipt in bloud, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 13. his face is like lightening, but lovely to his Saints, it ſhineth as the Sun; <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 16. this great power of the Lord Chriſt is known by his names and titles given him, he is called, <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Rev.</hi> 19. 16. King of Nations, <hi>Ier.</hi> 10. 7. King of Saints, a great King, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. all creatures are at his command, the hoſt of Heaven attend him, mighty to ſave, the <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 9.</note> Lord ſhall go forth like a Giant, he ſhall ſtir up courage like a man of war, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 13. a Wonderful Counſeller, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118067:11"/> his name is above all names, every knee ſhall bow to him, his Right hand ſhall doe terrible things, make waſte Mountains and Hils: he is that Little Stone cut out of the Mountayn withour hands, that ſhall break in peeces the Gold, Silver, Braſſe, and Iron, and Clay, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. all former Monarchicall Goverments, and he ſhall take to himſelfe great Power and Rule, he ſhall be King of the whol Earth, <hi>and there ſhall bee given to him Dominion and Glory, and a Kingdom, that all Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Nations, and Languages, ſhall ſerve him.</hi> Dan. 7. 14</p>
            <p>When will the Lord Chriſt take to him this great Power and reign as King? Firſt, when the enemies of his Church and Saints are at the higheſt and ſay, <hi>I ſit as Queen,</hi> Rev. 18. 7. when they ſay, <hi>I will aſcend above the Clouds, I will be like the moſt High,</hi> Iſa. 14. 14. when the enemies of <hi>God</hi> are lifted up with pride and power, then ſhall the Lord Chriſt make known his power; then ſhall her plagues come ſuddenly, for <note place="margin">Reve. 18. 7.</note> the Lord that judgeth her is a ſtrong <hi>God,</hi> then ſhall ſhe come down and ſit in the duſt. O how high were the enemies of <note place="margin">Iſa. 47. 1.</note> 
               <hi>God</hi> and of his Saints in this Land of late, how did they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Saints, how did they begin to rule over mens eſtates and conſciences too, and ſayd, <hi>bow-down that wee may go over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now will <hi>God</hi> make his enemies his footſtool, now will <hi>God</hi> viſit the wickedneſſe of the world, as it is in Eſay 13. 11. <hi>I will cauſe the arrogancy of the proud to ceaſe, and I will caſt down the pride of Tyrants:</hi> And is not this the work <hi>God</hi> is about in our dayes? and hath not <hi>God</hi> done much in theſe dayes? oh that men had eyes to ſee it, that <hi>God</hi> might have the glory.</p>
            <p>Secondly when the Saints are at the loweſt then will the Lord repent him ſelfe for his ſervants, when he ſeeth that their power is gone and they have no help left: how ſad was our <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 32. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> condition in <hi>England</hi> of late years, in the time of our Prelates, how did they oppreſs good men, making ſome fly to <hi>new-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> branding ſome, and cutting off their Eares, impriſoning others; how ſad was our condition this laſt yeare, when ſo black a cloud did ariſe both in <hi>Kent, Surrey, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Skot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and on the Seas; and how did wicked men thraten to cut
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118067:12"/> the throats of godly men and plunder them, then did <hi>Gods</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like <hi>Iſrael</hi> groan and cry unto the Lord; and prayſed bee our good <hi>God</hi> who hath ſcattered the proud, and hath taken our parts, and hath rayſed faithfull Inſtruments who have je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parded their lives in the High Places in the Field; oh let not ſuch valiant Commanders and Souldiers go without their due Honor, next to the honor of <hi>God:</hi> and though the Saints were low yet <hi>God</hi> was on high, and hee hath taken our part, when there was none to help, then <hi>Gods</hi> Arm brought Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, When wicked men rage againſt the Lord and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Saints, as in the ſecond Pſalm, <hi>Wherefore do the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then rage, and the people imagin a vain thing, the Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves and the Rulers take Counſell together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord and againſt his anoynted,</hi> Then <hi>will God ſet his King upon his holy Hill of Sion:</hi> verſe 6. when wicked men rage the Lord Chriſt ſhall daſh them in peeces like Potters veſſels; and never did wicked men rage more then of late, therefore ſure their ruine is near: did <hi>Saul</hi> proſper when hee raged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>David?</hi> did not <hi>God</hi> rend the Kingdom from him? and is not this the day when <hi>wicked men ſhall fret themſelves and curſe their God and their King, and look upward? Iſa.</hi> 8. 21. but bleſſed be <hi>God</hi> that the rage of man ſhall turn to his prayſe, and the remainder of wrath will he reſtrayn.</p>
            <p>When the Lord Chriſt comes to throw down Antichriſt and his adherents, he will ſhake all Nations in that day, in the day of his fierce anger, and by a mighty Earthquake turning <note place="margin">Eſay. 13. 13.</note> Kingdoms and Nations, upſide down, every one muſt endure a ſhaking in this Earthquake, and is not <hi>God</hi> now a ſhaking this Nation, and throwing down what Antichriſt hath built <note place="margin">Revel. 16. 18. 19</note> for many years: o! what a ſmoke doth this great ruinous houſe make! it blindeth the eyes of moſt men yea many godly men; ſurely in this ruinous heap Ieſus Chriſt the wiſe Builder will finde many precious ſtones, and many peeces of timber that are found at the heart and fit them to build the <hi>New Ieruſalem;</hi> though many great poſts will bee found rotten at the heart when they are tried, and they will be fit for nothing but for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118067:12"/> the fire; <hi>for behold the day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble; and the day cometh that ſhall burn them up ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, and it ſhall leave neither root nor branch;</hi> Mal. 4. 1. <hi>wicked men ſhall be as rubbidge, and he ſhall tread down the wicked, for they ſhall be as aſhes under the ſoles of his feet.</hi> Mal 4. 3.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Nations and Kingdoms that have lived in pomp, and contempt of God and his Saints ſhall ſuffer dreadful ſhakings, that no perſon, nor Nation, nor Government, ſhall be able to ſtand, that ſhall oppoſe the Kingly Government of the Lord Chriſt, for he hath ſaid, <hi>once more he will not only ſhake the earth; but the heavens alſo, Heb.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, When the Saints are in the dark as well as wicked men, much fearing and thinking of a dark Night that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with dreadfull troubles; and ſo it will be to all thoſe that are not acquainted what God is doing; when the Lord reigns <hi>clouds and darkneſſe are round about him, yet Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and judgment are the habitation of his Throne; and a fire ſhall go before him to burn up all his enemies,</hi> Pſalm 97. 2, 3. At the comming of Chriſt will be a dark time for at midnight the Bridegroom came. All thoſe that would be acquainted what the Lord Chriſt is doing, let them read Eſay 42. 16. <hi>He will lead the blinde by a way that they known not, and will lead them in paths that they have not known I will make darkneſſe light before them, and crooked things ſtraight, and not forſake them.</hi> Many ſay in our dayes, things go on as in untrodden paths and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known wayes and dark wayes; if you look into this Scripture you may ſee the Lord Chriſt will lead his peeple in ſuch a way as they have not known, and many good men are in the dark at this time, and godly Miniſters: if you read Eſay 42. 18. 19. 20. there he ſayth, <hi>who is ſo blinde as my ſervant? who is ſo blinde as he that is perfect, and blinde as the Lords</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118067:13"/> 
               <hi>Servant:</hi> but at laſt <hi>God</hi> will let them ſee, for <hi>at evening time it ſhall be light.</hi> Zak. 14. 7.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, when the Lord Chriſt fits and chuſes out ſome choice inſtruments for his work, ſuch as <hi>Moyſes, Ioſhua, Sampſon, David, Solomon, Cyrus, Zorobabel,</hi> or moddel out ſome Army, a <hi>Gideon</hi> and his three hundred men; when you ſee God raiſe up men of another ſpirit, choice men for wiſdom and courage, to do ſome notable work, as <hi>God</hi> hath done by this Army of late years; it is a ſign that God is doing ſome excellent work for his Church, and for the downfal of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Seaventhly, When the Lord Chriſt makes his Power known in abaſing proud men and women, as you may read in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third of <hi>Iſa.</hi> at large; there you may ſee, what God is doing now in theſe laſt days. Oh how hath God in this Land of late pulled down the pride of many tall Cedars! both in the Church as Lord Biſhops, and many great men are brought low; for the haughtineſs of man ſhall be abaſed, and the loftineſs of man ſhall be brought low, and the Lord alone exalted; in that day he ſhall tread them down, <hi>even by the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2. 9. Iſa. 26. 5, 6. Mat. 4. 3.</note> 
               <hi>feet of the poor and the ſteps of the needy;</hi> and ye ſhall tread down the wicked, for they ſhall be aſhes under the ſoles of your feet.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, When the Lord Chriſt gives his Saints a heart to cry mightily to God for the downfal of Antichriſt, and will give him no reſt till he makes <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the praiſe of the whole earth; when the Angel having the golden Cenſor, which was the prayers of the Saints powred out, then woe to Antichriſt; there was a voice of thunder, and lighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and an earthquake; how hath God made his power known by prayer? <hi>Moyſes</hi> prayed, and the Red-Sea ſtood on heaps, at <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> prayer the Sun ſtood ſtill: prayer will ſhut Heaven and open Heaven, as <hi>Eliah</hi> did; and hath not God raiſed up ſome men to a mighty ſpirit of prayer? how do they cry to God with abundance of confidence, believing now God is pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down Antichriſt? oh ſaith a poor gracious ſoul, let me pull too with my prayers, for it will never be well with <hi>Sion</hi> till Antichriſt be deſtroyed!</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118067:13"/>
            <p>Ninthly, When the Lord Chriſt begins to take the vayl off, that is ſpread over all Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 7. <hi>A fire ſhall go before him which ſhall</hi> give light to his people, but <hi>burn up all his enemies round about: the earth ſaw it and trembled. Pſa.</hi> 97. 3, 4. When the Sun of righteouſneſs ſhall ariſe, oh what a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there will be between <hi>Goſhen</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> and ſurely God hath of late more then formerly, opened the eys of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny godly men, and made known his truth concerning Chriſts Kingly Government in theſe laſt days; but when the reſt of the <hi>Gentles</hi> and <hi>Iews</hi> do come to the knowledg of Chriſt, oh how glorious will thoſe times be!</p>
            <p>But unto whom will the Lord Chriſt reveal this great work in deſtroying Antichriſt, and calling of the <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentles</hi> that are not yet called? They muſt be his friends as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, they muſt be ſuch as fear him, ſuch as dearly love him, and <note place="margin">Pſa. 25.</note> love not their lives to the death; precious choice men, <hi>Daniel</hi> like men of excellent ſpirits; men beloved of Chriſt as <hi>Iohn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reve. 12. 11.</note> was, lying in Chriſts boſom, Eagle-ey'd men, ſuch as the <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 27.</note> Shepheards were which watched by night, and ſpent their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations on the high things of God; men like <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Caleb,</hi> who followed the Lord fully, and will ſpeak well of the good Land; men that have much ſound knowledg of the <note place="margin">Numb. 14 22:</note> myſtery of Chriſts Kingdom, ſearching out the deep things of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 10.</note> God; they muſt be ſuch as have laid the Church troubles to their hearts, <hi>Iacobs</hi> that have wraſtled with God by prayer, <note place="margin">Ier. 9. 1.</note> and will have no denial; they are the firſt born ſons of <hi>Sion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 10. 2, 3.</note> ſuch as have ſpent themſelves in faſting and fervent crying to <hi>Iehovah; thoſe that have ſowen in tears, they ſhall reap with joy,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32. 24.</note> thoſe ſhall have the firſt fruits, and hear from Chriſt the firſt newes of <hi>Sions</hi> glory; theſe and theſe alone, ſhall ſee the Land a far of.</p>
            <p>What will the Lord Chriſt do in theſe laſt days by his Kingly <hi>Prerogative Power?</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, He will deſtroy his enemies.</item>
               <item>Secondly, He will exalt his Saints.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Lord Chriſt hath begun this work already, he hath trod the winepreſs of the wrath of the Almighty; this he did in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118067:14"/> the Garden, and on the Croſs, then he conquered all our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemies, then he ſuffered for us, but now he muſt reign till he hath made all his enemies his footſtool; theſe days will bring forth ſad news for Antichriſt and all his adherents, their judgments ſlumbreth not; <hi>A long time</hi> ſaith Chriſt <hi>I have held my peace, I have been ſtill, I have refrained my ſelf, now will I cry like a travelling woman, I will deſtroy and devoure at once; the Lord goes forth like a mighty man of war, he ſhall cry, yea roar, he ſhall prevaile againſt his enemies.</hi> When the Lyon <note place="margin">Iſa 32 23. 24.</note> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſhall rore, woe to the beaſts, woe to Antichriſt the great enemy of Chriſts Kingdom, and woe to all the Kings of the earth that have taken part with the Beaſt: woe to <hi>Rome</hi> and her conſederates, <hi>Howl ye, for the day of the Lord is at hand: it ſhall come as a deſtruction from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi> Iſa 13. 6. <hi>your lofty looks ſhall be laid low,</hi> Iſa. 2. 11. <hi>for the day of vengeance is in my heart, and the year of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed is come;</hi> it will be a terrible bloudy day to the Lord Chriſts enemies, as you may read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34. for his camp is very great, his day is very terrible, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 10, 11. he will make waſt as mountains and hills the greateſt of his enemies; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 15. the ruin of ſpiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be by a mighty earthquake; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 13. <hi>Rev</hi> 16. 16. at the taking of <hi>Babel</hi> the whole earth is moved, <hi>Ier.</hi> 50. 46. when the Lord Chriſt comes to make his power known in deſtroying his enemies, there will be great bloudy wars, and changes in in Governments, and great troubles in all Nations. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears plain by many places of Scripture, it will be bloudy times at the fall of Antichriſt, the Lord hath a conſumption to bring upon the whole earth; See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 15. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. 3, <hi>to the end, Chap.</hi> 28. 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 34. 8. where you may read how bloudy a time it will be, for it is the day of vengeance, and the year of recompence for the controverſie of <hi>Sion;</hi> it is comfortable for the Saints, though he that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judg the great whore, that hath made the earth drunk with her fornications, and to avenge the bloud of his ſervants; <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 20. the Lord Chriſt will make known his <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power</hi> in the throwing down of the man of ſin, he will ſtir
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118067:14"/> up jealouſie like a man of war, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 13. he will ſtrike through Kings in the day of his wrath, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 110. 5, 6. he ſhall be crowned King of Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. he ſhall reign till Antichriſt be utterly thrown down, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 8. it ſhall be as the overthrowing of <hi>Sodom,</hi> never to be inhabited from ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to generation, root &amp; branch ſhall be wholly deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as you may read, <hi>Ier.</hi> 50. 39, 40. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. 1. for the Stone cut out of the Mountain without hands, ſhall break in pieces the gold and the ſilver, the braſs, iron and the clay, and they ſhall become as chaff, and the wind ſhal carry them away, and this Stone ſhall become a great mountain, and fill the whole earth. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 35.</p>
            <p>Be incouraged O ye valiant Commanders, and Souldiers, and ſubjects of Chriſt: you that have ſought the Lords Battels, glory and boaſt in your great General the Lord Chriſt, he is a man of war mighty to ſave, a Giant refreſhed with wine, a Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> he hath a rod of Iron in his hands, he will ſtrike through Kings in the day of his wrath, he ſhall judge among the Nations, he ſhall fill the places with dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; the Sword of the Lord is filled with blood, for it is the day of the Lords vengeance, he will have his garments dipt in blood, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34. and the ſouls of the Heavens ſhall eat the fleſh of Kings and of mighty men. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 18. Woe to all the Kings of the earth, that oppoſe the Lord Chriſt when he comes to reign; for the pride of man ſhall be abaſed and the Lord alone exalted in that day; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 10. 11. he will pull down the Cedars, the mighty men, the greateſt of his enemies; and may we not think that <hi>God</hi> is going to throw down Antichriſt now in <hi>England?</hi> is not this one of the out-works of <hi>Rome?</hi> you know when Souldiers are againſt a City, they firſt ſtorm the Out-works: now I ſay, brave valiant Commanders, and Souldiers of the Lord Chriſt, you that have begun to pull down the Out-works of <hi>Rome,</hi> go on and fight ſtoutly for your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral the Lord Chriſt, you ſhall ſee him do more wonders for you; and who knoweth but you may be counted worthy to be choſen, and ſaithful, to ſet up your Trophies of triumph on the Walls of <hi>Rome;</hi> which will ere long be done.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118067:15"/>
            <p>Alſo, the Lord Chriſt will make his power known, in tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Satan under his feet, principalities and powers muſt be ſubject unto him; when Chriſt reigns Satan muſt be bound up. <hi>And I ſaw an Angel come down from Heaven, having the Key of the bottomleſs pit, and a great chain in his hand; and he laid hold on the Dragon, that old Serpent, which is the Devil, and he was bound up a thouſand years. Rev.</hi> 20. 1, 2, 3, 10. When we ſee that devilliſh malice in men againſt <hi>God</hi> and his Saints is taken away; then ſhall the Lyon and the Lamb ly down together, they ſhall not hurt in my holy Mountain; then ſhall we beat our ſwords into pruning hooks. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2. 4.</p>
            <p>We have ſpoken of Chriſts <hi>Prerogative power</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of his enemies, and making them his footſtool; but after this dark night of trouble, <hi>will the Son of righteouſneſs ariſe with healing in his wings,</hi> when he hath troden the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>and they ſhall beas aſhes under the ſoals of his feet; Mal.</hi> 4. 2, 3. Oh the happy times that then will be! <hi>thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his glory, Iſa.</hi> 33. 17. <hi>he ſhall be King of the whole earth, Zach.</hi> 14. 9. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 19. <hi>his Kingdom ſhall laſt for ever, Iſa.</hi> 59. 19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 14. that is, to the end of the world; and then ſhall he reſign up the Kingdom to his Father, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 3. and God ſhall be all in all. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Under this glorious Kingly Government, of the Lord Chriſt, his great Power ſhall appear, in teaching his Saints, abundance of knowledg ſhall be in the earth; <hi>for the earth ſhall be fill'd with the knowledg of the Lord, as the waters cover the Sea,</hi> and it muſt needs <note place="margin">Iſa. 11. 9.</note> be ſo: <hi>for thy Children ſhall be all taught of the Lord;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 54. 13.</note> In the laſt days of the <hi>Kingly Government</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>God will powre out his ſpirit upon all fleſh, and their ſons and their daughters ſhall Prophecy; many ſhall run too and fro, and knowledg ſhall encreaſe; That City had no</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioel 2. 28. Dan. 12. 4.</note> 
               <hi>need of the Sun nor of the Moon to ſhine in it, for the</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118067:15"/> 
               <hi>glory of the Lord did light it, and the Lamb is the light thereof.</hi> Oh how little hath been known of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and of the Kingly Government of Chriſt in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times! and how abundantly doth it now ſpread; but oh how glorious will the times be when Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall be deſtroyed! and the <hi>Iews</hi> called; then will all the fulneſs of theſe promiſes be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Under this Kingly Government of the Lord Chriſt there ſhall be greater degrees of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs among the Saints, yea, <hi>the beauty of holineſs; in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 110. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the new</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>upon all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſels, and upon the horſe Bridles ſhall be holineſs to the Lord, and an high</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zech. 14. 20.</note> 
               <hi>way ſhall be there, and it ſhall be called the way of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 35. 8. Revel. 21.</note> 
               <hi>And I</hi> Iohn <hi>ſaw the holy City, the new</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>come down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride adorned for her Husband, and all the ſtones of that City are precious ſtones;</hi> which doth ſet forth that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Church, under the Kingly Government of the Lord Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There ſhall abundance of peace and plenty be under the Government of the Lord Chriſt; he will firſt be like <hi>David,</hi> a man of war; but after that be done, then he will be like <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> peace and plenty will be in thoſe days; when once <hi>Ioſhua</hi> appears in his glory, <hi>he will bring down the noiſe of ſtrangers, and the branch of the terrible ones ſhall be brought low Iſa.</hi> 25. 5. <hi>the ſons of them that afflicted thee shall come bonding unto thee, and all they that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed thee, shall bow themſelves at the ſoles of thy feet; &amp; they shall call thee the City of the Lord, the Sion of the holy One of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 14. <hi>&amp; for plenty for braſs I will</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118067:16"/> 
               <hi>bring gold and for iron I will bring ſilver, and for wood braſs, and for ſtones iron: I will alſo make thy Officers be at peace, and thine exactors righteouſneſs;</hi> verſe 17. <hi>the Wolf shall dwell with the Lamb and the Leopard shall ly down with the Kid,</hi> at the glorious times of peace, in the days of Chriſts Kingly Government; for he is the King of peace, and the Prince of peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6. he will create peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 19. truth and peace ſhall kiſs one another under this Kings reign.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, under this peaceable reign of the Lord Chriſt, there ſhall be a very fruitful time, the <hi>New Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall ſo encreaſe, that it ſhall over-ſpread many Countreys, <hi>and all Nations shall flow into it, Iſa</hi> 2. 2 <hi>then shall they come flocking as Doves to Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes; Iſa</hi> 60. 8. his peeple ſhall be a willing pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the day of his power, then ſhall the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffer violence; <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 12. <hi>Bashan</hi> was a fruitful Hill, but Mount <hi>Sion</hi> far excells it, the valeys ſhall be full of ſprings, and crouded with Corn, <hi>Eſay</hi> 41. 18. they ſhall ſhoot for joy and ſing; <hi>the Church shall be as the garden of</hi> Eden, <hi>as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Lord, Eſay</hi> 51. 3. this is a fruitful time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others as you may reade, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 25. 26. <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8. 5. from ſmall beginnings, it ſhall grow up into a Mountain, and ſhall fill the whole earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 34, 35. <hi>then shall the Kingdoms, and Dominions, and greatneſs of the Kingdoms under the whole Heavens be given to the Saints of the moſt High.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The laſt great act of the Lord Chriſt; Power is, in the duration of this glorious Church: it ſhall laſt for ever, as long as the world ſhall laſt, as you may read, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 27. <hi>his Kingdom is an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, and of his Kingdom there shall be no</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118067:16"/> 
               <hi>end, Dan.</hi> 2. 44. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 33. <hi>Eſay</hi> 54 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 61. 7. <hi>and his Dominion is an everlaſting Dominion, which shall not paſs away and of his Kingdom shall not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, Dan.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>and the Saints of the moſt High shall take the Kingdom, and poſſeſs the Kingdom for ever,</hi> even for ever and ever. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 3. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 16. 17.</p>
            <p>Oh the happy and bleſſed times that will be under the Kingly Government of the Lord Chriſt! when Antichriſt ſhall be utterly deſtroyed, and the <hi>Jews</hi> and fullneſs of the <hi>Gentles</hi> come in; When Knowledg ſhall cover the earth, as waters cover the Sea, and holineſs abound in men, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of all Ordinances, and peace and plenty, that which the creatures now groan for; <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 22. the Lyon and the Lamb ſhall ly down together, then we ſhall beat our ſwords into Plow ſhares, and our ſpears into pruning hooks; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. 4. and I will make the place of my feet glorious, the ſons of them that afflicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee, and all thoſe that deſpiſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves at the ſoles of thy feet; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 14. <hi>and the Kingdom and Dominion, and the greatneſs of the Kingdoms under the whole Heavens, ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt High, whoſe Kingdom is an everlaſting Kingdom, and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him. Dan.</hi> 7. 27.</p>
            <p>Oh that the Lord would open our eyes to ſee the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and beauty of Chriſts Kingdom! and pardon our too much neglect of ſearching the Scriptures, concerning the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things of <hi>Sions</hi> beauty; which will be ere long the joy of the whole earth, the glory and praiſe of the whole world, <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 62. 7. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 48. 2.) in ſpite of men and Devils, and all the Powers in the world, and of Hell it ſelf.</p>
            <closer>Thy Kingdom come Amen, Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
